我们都知道阿波罗计划的主要目标是什么
We all know what the major goal of the Apollo program was,
就是在60年代末将人类送上月球
to put a man on the moon by the end of the 1960s
主要是为了打败苏联人 证明所谓"资本主义优于共产主义"
basically to beat the Soviets and prove that the capitalist system was better than the communist one.
但是等登月成功了 那些已经开发的硬件、火箭、航天器等技术将何去何从?
But once that's done what would happen the hardware,
the rockets, spacecraft and technology that had been developed,
更不用说参与到阿波罗工程里的40万名工人
not to mention the 400,000 workers that helped build them,
如果不充分利用他们取得的成果 那阿波罗250亿美元经费就太浪费了
it would be a waste not to capitalize on gains they had made
and make the most of the $25 billion that would have been spent.
为此在1965年 早在第一次登月之前
To this end in 1965, well before the first moon landing,
就出现了一个名为"土星阿波罗应用"的计划 后来改为"阿波罗应用计划"
a program called Saturn Apollo Applications, which later became the Apollo Applications Program
以在首批登月后利用阿波罗的硬件执行一系列其他任务
was created to utilise the Apollo hardware for a range of other duties after the initial moon landings,
因此在本期视频中 我们将看到决策者眼中70年代的阿波罗会怎样大放光芒
so in this video, we'll look at what the planners thought Apollo might have gone on to do in the 1970s
以及阿波罗1号的火灾是如何改变一切的
and how the Apollo 1 fire changed everything.
接下来是片头与工商时间 正片空降坐标2:20
阿波罗应用计划是包括韦恩赫尔·冯·布劳恩在内的规划者
The Apollo Applications Program was what the planners including Werner Von Bruan
希望阿波罗计划在完成首批登月之后能够继续发展而想出的
hoped Apollo would lead on to once the initial moon landing had been completed.
此时仍是太空探索的早期阶段 如我们之前关于天空实验室的视频中所见
This was still an early time for space exploration and as we saw in a previous video about Skylab,
我们可能已经登上了月球 但我们其实并不知道如何在太空中长期工作生活
we may well have gone to the moon but we didn't really know how to live and work in space for long periods.
阿波罗应用计划将利用已经开发的东西
The Apollo Applications Program would take what had developed and run with it
来开发人类不仅在太空中、还能在月球上生活的能力
to help develop our abilities to not only live in space but also on the moon.
在1965年 根据资金维持情况有两条可能的路线
In 1965 there were two possible routes depending on how the funding would hold up.
第一种情况下
The first "Case 1" scenario
登月任务之后将不再订购土星火箭与阿波罗飞船的硬件
was that there would be no further Saturn Apollo hardware ordered past that of the moon missions.
即使有这些限制 土星-阿波罗项目组仍认为到1973年底会打21发土星1B
Even with these limitations, the Saturn Apollo Office thought there would 21 Saturn 1B launches,
(土星1B是土星五号没有一级的短版本 火箭是在抬高的支架上发射的
(that's the shorter version without the main 1st stage that sat on the milk stool launch pad
用于发射较轻的载荷)
and would be used for lighter loads)
到1973年底还有15次全尺寸土星五号的发射
and 15 full-sized Saturn V launches by the end of 1973.
第二种情况将极大化利用土星-阿波罗的能力
The second “Case 2” scenario would see an extensive utilization of Saturn Apollo capabilities,
会更早地聚焦于"后阿波罗时期"的国家太空目标
with an earlier focus on a post-Apollo national space objective,
这些额外的发射任务将在登月和其他任务之间交错进行
these extra launches would interleave between the moon landings and other missions.
"Wet Workshop"空间站,也叫"湿车间",是使用一个废火箭级作为临时空间站的想法.
包括使用土星五号火箭上面级的燃料箱作为湿车间
These would include using the fuel tank of the upper stage of a Saturn V rocket as a wet workshop.
燃料箱中的燃料用完后 剩余的燃料会排放到太空中
Once the fuel in the tank was spent, instead of just jettisoning it they would vent any fuel left into space
然后将内部作为居住舱与湿车间
and then use the interior as a habitat and workshop.
该想法后被用于天空实验室
This idea would be later used for Skylab,
虽然那属于"干车间" 因为它是专为任务制造的 从未被用作燃料箱
though that was a dry workshop as it was purpose-built for the task never used as a fuel tank in space.
登月计划有四个阶段
There were four planned phases to the moon landings.
第一阶段是1969年到1971年 第一批人登陆月球并在四次任务中积累经验
Phase 1 was from 1969 to 1971 which would land the first men on the moon
and build up experience over the four missions.
对应阿波罗11到14号
These missions corresponded to Apollo 11 to 14.
第二阶段是1972年到1973年 月球探索阶段
Phase 2 from 1972 to 1973 would be the Lunar Exploration Phase,
这些任务将在月球停留更长的时间 并带来包括月球车在内的更大载荷
these missions would stay for longer duration and bring larger payloads including the Lunar rover,
对应阿波罗15到17号
these ended up corresponding to Apollo 15 to 17.
第三阶段在1974年进行 是一次月球勘测任务
Phase 3 was pencilled in for 1974 and was a lunar Oritbal Survey mission
有点像阿波罗8号 但只有两名宇航员 而不是三名
which would be a bit like Apollo 8 but with two astronauts instead of 3
而且只有指令舱和服务舱 没有登月舱
and with just the Command and Service Module without the Lunar Module.
飞船将进入月球极地轨道飞行28天
This would enter a polar orbit around the moon for 28 days
利用胶片相机 磁力计 雷达测高仪 伽马射线光谱仪与服务舱中的微陨石收集板
and observe the whole surface of the moon with a suite of instruments including film cameras, a magnetometer,
等一整套设备仪器观察整个月球表面
a radar altimeter, a gamma-ray spectrometer, and micrometeoroid collection plates in the Service Module.
这项工作最终交由月球勘测轨道飞行器(LRO)来完成
This job would eventually be done in much greater detail
勘测细节更丰富 持续时间更长
and for much longer by the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter robotic probe
月球勘测轨道飞行器
且从2009年开始持续至今
starting in 2009 and is still going today.
第四阶段是1975年到1976年 为月球表面会合与探索阶段
Phase 4 would be from 1975 to 1976 and would be the Lunar Surface Rendezvous and Exploration Phase
包括一组两次发射的任务
and would consist of a dual launch mission.
一次发射将向月球表面发送一艘改装的月球有效载荷舱(LPM)
The first would deliver a modified Lunar Payload Module or LPM to the surface of the moon,
本质是一个登月舱 但没有上升发动机与相关部件及燃料箱
basically a Lunar Module but without the ascent engines and associated parts and fuel tanks
使其具有更大的运输食物和科学设备的能力
to give it a greater payload capability including food and scientific equipment.
并将作为宇航员在3个月后到达的住所
This would act as a shelter for when the astronauts arrived up to 3 months later.
任务的第二部分就是把宇航员送到那 着陆在第一发的登月舱附近
The second part of the mission would be when the astronauts arrived
and would land them near the Lunar Module Shelter,
之后任务将在月表停留长达14天
the mission would then stay on the surface for up to 14 days.
根据设想 这些经过一段时间的建设将发展成一个月球基地
It was envisioned that over time this basic setup would evolve into a lunar base
有更大的居住舱 且由核反应堆提供动力
with larger shelters powered by a nuclear reactor
有长途月球车 最多可容纳6人一次停留半年
with long-range rovers and up to 6 men staying for 6 months or 180 days at a time.
另一个计划是用土星五号载人飞越金星
Another plan was a manned flypast of Venus
用土星五号送搭载三人乘组的指令舱与服务舱
with a Saturn V used to send a three-man crew which would flypast in the Command and Service Module
和土星1B火箭的二级燃料箱对接 完成飞跃
attached to the second stage fuel tank of a Saturn 1B.
二级的燃料用光后
Once the fuel had been used,
燃料箱会作为供乘员在分离返回地球前居住的湿车间使用
the tank would be used as a wet workshop where the crew live on the return journey
before separating and returning to Earth.
但这些阿波罗应用计划的任务取决于资金的多少
But these Apollo Application Program missions were contingent on the funding
每年大约能从国会那讨来4.5亿美元的资金支持
which was around $450 Million per year being supported by congress
为了让国会满意 NASA必须在不出"重大问题"的情况下完成他们的计划
and to keep congress happy NASA have to deliver on what they had planned with no major hitches.
这个"重大问题"于1967年1月27日 在阿波罗一号上发生了
This is where a massive spanner was thrown into the works with the Apollo 1 fire on January 27th, 1967
宇航员维吉尔·格里森、爱德华·怀特与罗杰·查菲在一次"拔除插头"测试中丧生
which claimed the lives of astronauts “Gus” Grissom, Ed White, and Roger Chaffee during a plugs-out test,
本质上是火箭不加燃料的一次模拟发射演练
basically a full simulation test of a launch but without fuel in the rocket.
这对阿波罗计划是一个巨大的打击 导致了整个计划的重大改革
This was a huge blow to Apollo and would lead to a major overhaul of the whole program
但有人认为这也算是某种因祸得福
but some say that it was a blessing in disguise.
其原因是NASA一直在争分夺秒地遵守在60年代末将人类送上月球的最后期限
The reasoning behind this was that NASA had been racing to keep to the deadline
of putting a man on the moon by the end of the 1960s
并采取了某些所谓"不可接受的风险"以节省开支和成本
and had taken what some say were unacceptable risks to cut corners and costs.
阿波罗1号指令舱是早期的设计型号
The Apollo 1 Command Module was an early design
依赖于在太空中保持内部低压纯氧环境以节省重量和复杂性
that relied upon a low-pressure pure oxygen environment in space to save weight and complexity
而不是像我们在地球上呼吸的氮氧混合的空气
compared to a nitrogen/oxygen mix more like we breathe on earth.
舱门也被设计成向内打开
The hatch door was also designed to open inwards,
因此当火灾发生时 舱内的压力增加
so when the fire took hold the pressure in the cabin increased
三名宇航员无法从内部打开舱门
making it impossible for the crew to open the door from the inside.
水星和双子座任务也使用了纯氧环境
The Mercury and Gemini missions also used a pure oxygen environment
有人认为之前用着好好的
and there was the thinking that because there had been no issues there
那同样的纯氧舱内环境放到阿波罗上肯定也不会出问题
then the same pure oxygen environment would work for Apollo,
尽管设计要复杂得多 风险也大得多
even though it was a much more complicated design and the risks were considerably greater.
对航天工业的一些人来说 这是一个事故隐患
To some in the space industry, this was an accident waiting to happen
如果阿波罗1号测试成功 并且该计划继续采用这种原始设计
and that if the Apollo 1 test had worked and the program had gone ahead with this original design,
那这种事故很可能会在真正的发射中发生 导致人箭俱损
this kind of accident would probably have happened during a real launch
with the subsequent loss of the crew and vehicle.
从这个角度来看 如果真发生这种事故
From that standpoint, it would have been much harder if not impossible
在太空还不太可能找到原因 那阿波罗计划可能直接就被毙了
to try and find the root cause of the exit and could well have ended the program there and then.
事实上 我们仍然不知道具体是什么引发了阿波罗1号指令舱的火灾
In fact, we still don't know exactly what triggered the fire in the Command Module of Apollo 1
只有所谓"最可能"的原因 即一束短路的电线
apart from the "most" likely cause was a short circuit in a bundle of wires.
值得庆幸的是事故发生在测试期间 飞船就在发射台上
One saving grace was that it happened during a test when it was on the launchpad
所以指令舱仍然完好无损 可以对细节进行严格的取证
so the Command Module was still intact and could be gone over in exacting forensic detail.
这场火灾将项目推迟了21个月
The fire delayed the program for 21 months
在此期间 指令舱和其他系统进行了重大的设计更新
in which time there was a major redesign of the Command Module and other systems
并调整了NASA的工作方法
and a shake-up of NASA's working practices
更加强调安全 尤其是消防安全
that had a much greater emphasis on safety and fire in particular.
但所有这一切都发生在越南战争成本上升的同时
But all this came at the same time as the cost of the Vietnam war was spiralled upwards
林登·约翰逊想推出他的版本的罗斯福新政
and President Lyndon Johnson wanted to introduce his version of Roosevelt's New Deal
政策名为"伟大社会"
called the Great Society,
一套通过消除贫困和种族不公正来平息民间动乱的国内计划
a set of domestic programs to quell civil unrest by eliminating poverty and racial injustice
预算保持在1000亿美元内
and keep within a $100 billion budget.
由于所有这些利益的相互竞争
With all these competing interests
以及国会对NASA在阿波罗1号大火中的表现感到不满
and congress's displeasure with NASA's performance around the Apollo 1 fire,
阿波罗项目在削减预算的名单中首当其冲
it meant that it was on the top of the list for budget cuts.
国会不能把整个计划砍掉
They couldn't cut the whole program
因为这样会违背肯尼迪总统在1961年作出的承诺
because that would renege of the promise that President Kennedy had made in 1961
但他们可以通过预算从4.5亿美元砍到1.22亿美元来浇灭"后阿波罗应用计划"
but what they could do was to put a halt to the post-Apollo Applications Program
登月舱中继实验室
但他们可以通过预算从4.5亿美元砍到1.22亿美元来浇灭"后阿波罗应用计划"
by cutting by effectively cutting its budget from $450 Million to $122 million,
这样的削减持续到了1970年尼克松总统时期
a slide which continued under President Nixon in 1970.
原定的阿波罗20号取消 其土星火箭被重新指派发射天体实验室
The scheduled Apollo 20 was cancelled and its Saturn was redesignated to launch Skylab
天空实验室是阿波罗应用计划中少有的生产出来的成品
成为NASA"后阿波罗时期"计划的重点
which would become the focus for NASA's post-Apollo plan
直到航天飞机在1979年投入使用 虽然最后推迟到了1981年
until the Space shuttle was meant to come into service in 1979, though that eventually turned into 1981.
由于月球轨道勘测被取消
Further reductions came as the Lunar orbital survey was cancelled
登月任务也因阿波罗18号和19号被取消而缩短
and the moon missions were cut short with the cancellation of Apollo 18 and 19
导致阿波罗17号变成了第六次 也是最后一次阿波罗载人登月任务
leaving Apollo 17 as the 6th and last Apollo manned mission to the moon.
还有两枚土星火箭被用于随后的天空实验室任务和阿波罗-联盟对接任务
Two more Saturn rockets were used on the following Skylab missions and one on the Apollo Soyuz mission
1975年美国的阿波罗飞船指令舱与服务舱 同苏联的联盟号飞船对接
where the American Apollo Command and Service Module docked with the Soviet Soyuz capsule in 1975
两国宇航员在太空的这次握手
and the handshake between the two crews
似乎为18年前由苏联人造卫星1号的发射而开启的太空竞赛画上了圆满的句号
seemed a fitting end to the Space race which began 18 years earlier with the launch of the Soviet Sputnik 1.
感谢大家观看
So I hope you liked the video and if you did then please, thumbs up,
click the bell notification, subscribe and share and don't forget Patreon supporters
get ad-free versions before they go public on Youtube.